Evan Hill Papers 1987.0003
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Evan Hill Papers
1880-1987
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1987.0003
14.4 Linear Feet
The collection contains the research and publications of Evan Hill, journalism professor, and head of the journbalism department, at the University of Connecticut from 1965 to 1984.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center in 1987.
Biography
Evan Hill, born in Philadelphia, Pennsylvannia, was an emeritus professor of journalism at the University of Connecticut and the son of Marie Schmeltz Hill and Louis Hill. He received his Bachelor of Arts from Stanford University in 1948 and his Master of Science degree from Boston University in 1950. He married Priscilla Fiske in 1946.
As a young man, Hill worked as a reporter and editor on newspapers in the state of ashington and in the Alaska territory before World War II. In September 1941, he went on active duty with the Alaska National Guard as a second lieutenant. Hill volunteered for combat and fought with the 79th Infantry Division in Belgium and France. He was severely wounded in northern France and hospitalized for nearly four years, during which time he began to write non-fiction magazine articles, and sold an article on wounded soldiers to this first national publication, Liberty. Hill was discharged from the Army at the rank of captain.
Hill then served as editor of the Argus Champion, at that time a semi-weekly newspaper in Newport, N.H. After receiving his master's at Boston University, he stayed on for seven years as a journalism professor. In 1956, Hill joined the journalism faculty at Ohio State University, before beginning a seven-year stint working out of his office on Main Street in Newport as a fulltime freelance non-fiction magazine writer for the Saturday Evening Post, the Reader's Digest, Redbook, the New York Times Magazine, the Saturday Review, Yankee and others and reporting throughout the United States, Canada and Europe. His work has been translated into five languages. Hill also ghost-wrote books and magazines for U.S. cabinet officers, federal court judges and clergymen.
In 1965, Hill was appointed head of the journalism department at the University of Connecticut and served in that position until he retired in 1984. He published approximately 160 magazine articles and eight non-fiction books, twice with co-authors, including a college journalism textbook. Hill was an occasional consultant to several newspapers, including the Boston Globe and the Providence Journal. In 1950, he was the winner of the annual essay contest of the American Newspaper Publishers' Association, and Freedom Foundation award.
Hill was a director of The Day Publishing Company of New London, Connecticut and a trustee of the Bodenwein Foundation from 1978 to 1989, a trustee of the Richards Library in Newport and a member of the Newport School Board, the Budget Advisory committee and was an early member of the Newport Planning Board. For several years after his retirement he taught after school writing courses to Newport students and to adults in after-hours classes. Hill compiled a Historical Chronology of the History of Newport, designed to aid local historians, it is available on the web.
Hill was especially proud of the success of his former students, some of whom have been reporters and editors at the Boston Globe, New York Times, Time Magazine, the Wall Street Journal and other prominent publications. Many achieved executive positions in corporate public relations. Many of his students became his friends after their graduation and kept in touch with him until his death.
Hill died on Saturday April 10, 2010, at the age of ninety-one.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the research and publications of Evan Hill, journalism professor, and head of the jourbalism department, at the University of Connecticut from 1965 to 1984. His papers include notes and research that he compiled about the history of the University of Connecticut, as well as his own correspondence. Included are published documents, unpublished manuscripts, biographies of university presidents and alumni, speeches, notebooks, reference books, photographs, annual reports, and other miscellaneous notes.
Bumper stickers; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Ephemera (general object genre); Fliers (printed matter); Histories; Research (document genres); Notes; Publications (documents); Notebooks; Negatives (photographs); Realia; Photographic prints; Archives (institutions); Memorabilia; Monographs; Administrative records; University of Connecticut
- Series I: University History research, undated, circa 1870-1981
  - Academic Affairs (General), 1898-1922 (Box 7)
  - Allied Health Professions, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Alumni, 1978 (Box 7)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1978-1981 (Box 7)
  - Blanchette maps, undated, circa 1870-1980 (Box 3)
  - Books (10), notes, administrative records, transcripts, publications, 1978, 1980 (Box 5)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects include: Connecticut History, University of Connecticut History, Agriculture.]
  - Branches, 1967-1980 (Box 7)
  - Buildings (named for and landmark), undated (Box 7)
  - Buildings -- Chronology, circa 1981 (Box 3)
  - Center for Black Studies, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Chronology 1896-1918, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Chronology 1920-1944, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Chronology 1945-1959, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Chronology 1960-1970, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Chronology 1971-1982, circa 1981 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, books (6), administrative records, transcripts, notes, manuscripts, photographs, postcards, 1929, 1936, 1944, 1956, 1959, 1960, 1979, 1980 (Box 1)
    [Subjects include: Nonfictional Accounts, University of Connecticut History, Storrs, Connecticut History, Journalism Department Faculty, Department of English.]
  - Clippings, correspondences, notes, manuscripts, photographs, fliers, ephemera, 1950, 1968, 1969, 1970, 1981, 1984 (Box 6)
    [Subjects: Social Action and Protest, University of Connecticut History, Anti-Recruitment Protest, Dissident Faculty, Storrs, Connecticut History.]
  - Clippings, notes, administrative records, manuscripts, publications, 1953, 1979, 1980, 1981 (Box 2)
    [Subjects include: University of Connecticut History, University of Connecticut Buildings, Albert N. Jorgensen, University of Connecticut Athletics, Journalism Department.]
  - College of Agriculture, 1916-1979; 1972-1979 (Box 7)
  - Connecticut, Impact on, 1969-1980 (Box 7)
  - Connecticut, State of relations with Legislature, Governor, Budgets, 1979 (Box 7)
  - Continuing and Extended Education, undated, 1953-1978 (Box 7)
  - Extension service, 1963 (Box 7)
  - Faculty affairs, undated (Box 7)
  - Fine Arts, undated (Box 7)
  - Fort Trumbull Branch, 1947-1978 (Box 7)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes 8x10 B&W photographs supplied by Dr. Weber (campus administrator ?)
  - Fraternities, 1921-1983; 1980-1983 (Box 7)
  - Gerontology, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Graduate School, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Greeks, 1932-1978 (Box 7)
  - Health Center, 1974-1978 (Box 7)
  - Higher Education, Trends in, 1935-1978 (Box 7)
  - Home Economics, 1978, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Honors program, 1969-1979 (Box 7)
  - Husky Network, 1924-1980 (Box 7)
  - Index -- Alumni, circa 1981 (Box 3)
  - Infirmary (Student health), undated (Box 7)
  - Inner College, 1971 (Box 7)
    Includes photographs.
  - Institute of Materials Sciences, 1975-1978 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Urban Research, 1963-1975 (Box 3)
  - Jorgensen Auditorium, 1955-1978 (Box 3)
  - The Laurel, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1964-1978 (Box 7)
  - Maps of campus, circa 1870-1980 (Box 3)
  - Marching Band, undated, 1946-1978 (Box 3)
  - Marine Sciences Institute, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Minorities, undated, 1967-1978 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper advertisers, 1896-1980 (Box 3)
  - Notes, publications, clippings, books (4), maps (Storrs, Connecticut), financial records, administrative records, 1915, 1955, 1956, 1964, 1979, 1980 (Box 4)
    [Subjects include: Journalism Department, Historical Chronologies, University of Connecticut History, Storrs, Connecticut History.]
  - Oral histories, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Pharmacy, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, notes, manuscripts, clippings, 1958, 1960, 1970 (Box 8)
    [Subjects include: University of Connecticut History, Photographs, Historical Photographs (contains extensive collection of historical University photographs).]
  - Pied Piper, 1928-1980 (Box 3)
  - Pig Roast, the Bag Rush..., 1981 (Box 3)
  - Religious life (Catholic, Baptist, Lutheran, Congregational, Jewish), 1941 (Box 3)
  - ROTC -- Military training, 1959-1979 (Box 3)
  - School of Business, 1974-1978 (Box 7)
  - School of Education, 1963-1971 (Box 7)
  - School of Engineering, 1956, 1978 (Box 7)
  - School of Insurance, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - School of Law, 1968-1978 (Box 3)
  - School of Nursing, 1942-1978 (Box 3)
  - School of Social Work, 1946-1980 (Box 3)
  - Social and intellectual development, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Special Student Services, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Sports, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Sports notes, undated, 1928-1981 (Box 3)
  - Statistics, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Student Activities -- Student Union, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Student government, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Student Life -- Student Government, undated, 1935-1980 (Box 3)
  - Students -- Statistics, circa 1981 (Box 3)
  - Transportation, 1901-1978 (Box 3)
  - UConn, undated, 1938 (Box 7)
  - University Libraries, undated, 1930-1980 (Box 3)
- Series II: Photographs, 1900-1980 (Box 9)
  - 1900-1920
  - 1931-1940
  - 1941-1950
  - 1921-1930
  - 1951-1960
  - 1961-1970
  - 1971-1980
  - Graduation, undated, 1931-1980
  - World War I-Vietnam, 1918-1970s
  - The Rock, 1970-1973
  - Rope Pull, 1918-1970
  - Studying (student activities--very little studying), undated
  - Registration (first day), undated, 1976
  - Aerial views of campus, 1950s
  - Aerial views of campus, 1950s
  - Building list photographs, undated
  - Lynette Goodstine's SDS negatives (negatives and contact sheets), 1968
  - Chronology, undated
  - Winter, undated, 1969-1978
  - Mansfield tutorial, undated
  - Mrs. J's pictures, undated
  - Puerto Rican Center, undated, 1977
  - Marine Sciences, 1970-1972
  - International Fair, 1971
  - Law School, undated, 1968
  - Handicapped, undated, 1973
  - Health Center, undated, 1971-1977
  - Faculty, 1972-1978
  - Branches, undated, 1968-1974
  - Troubled years, 1963-1971
  - 1880-1900